Your Majesty
陛下
Why have you come here?
您怎么到这儿来了
Rise
起来吧
Your Majesty
陛下
You shouldn't move around
您还是别乱动了
It's cold now
现在天冷
When the weather warms up later
等过段时间天气暖和了
I'll take you for a good walk
我带您好好溜一圈
What
怎么
Is there something wrong with my body?
朕的身体 有什么问题么
Your Majesty
陛下
Of course there's nothing wrong with Your Majesty's body
陛下的身体当然没什么问题
You then
就你了
Take a team
带一队人马
With me
和我一起
Following behind Your Majesty
跟在陛下后面
I promise you all
我向诸位保证
Great Xuan has never forgotten the people of the north
大宣未有一日忘记北地子民
The royal army will recover the lost territories
王师必定收复故土
And restore peace to all
还大家一个太平天下
This northern expedition
北伐这事啊
You're risking your life for it
就你拿命干
Xuan Kingdom's greatest enemy
宣国最大的敌人
Has never been in the north
从来就不在北方
Minister Chen means
陈相的意思是
What else does Your Highness want?
殿下还想要什么
My friendship
我的友情
Does Your Highness dare to want it?
殿下敢要吗
We're not yet established
咱们立足未稳
It's not yet time to move against them
还不是动他们的时候
Today the Ministry of Revenue calculated tax revenue
今天户部综算税银收入
Totaling over 18 million taels
共计一千八百万余两
Can shield Your Highness from wind and rain, block swords and spears
能为殿下遮风雨 阻刀枪
It is Huan's fortune
是桓之幸
Your Highness, this old minister finally sees you
殿下 老臣终于见到你了
Everyone has their own account in their heart
每个人心里都有一笔账
If you stay away too long
你要是 在外头待久了
I'll name the child myself
我就自己给孩子取名字
Speaking of defeat before the battle
还未战先言败
Since it's a fight to the death, I won't be a coward
既要死战 我也不当此等孬种
Your Majesty, what do you need?
陛下 您有什么事
Just order your servant to do it
直接吩咐臣去做就是了
Five hundred it is
五百就五百
Five hundred men strike first
五百人先下手为强
No more talk, come
别跟他废话 来
Prince of Jin is rebelling
晋王谋反
I am ordered to capture him
我奉命捉拿
Surrender
束手就擒
And your lives will be spared
可保尔等性命
This northern expedition
此次北伐
Our goal is to recapture Beiyu Pass
我们的目标是夺回北域关
Your Highness, Prince of Jin
晋王殿下
I'm Liu Dadao
俺叫刘大刀
Commander of the Yong'an Garrison Left Army
乃永安戍卫左军统领
Old brother, beat the drums for me
老兄弟 给俺擂鼓
Liu, Liu Nian
刘 刘念
Your Majesty
陛下
When you were in Yiyang, you promised Grandfather
你在弋阳的时候答应过爷爷
To protect your servant for a lifetime of peace and joy
要护臣妾一世平安喜乐
Your daughter bids farewell
女儿拜别
May Father Emperor take care of his sacred body
望父皇圣体珍重
Do you think the people kneel to you for nothing?
你以为百姓凭什么跪你
They kneel to me, to Princess Xunyang
跪我 跪她浔阳公主
Can't catch a wolf without sacrificing the child
舍不得孩子套不着狼
Your son is willing to be the vanguard
儿臣 愿为先锋
Murong Cui of Yan Dong
燕东慕容崔
By order of Princess Xunyang
奉浔阳公主之命
Come to reinforce
前来驰援
It's all because of that Xuan Kingdom emperor
都是那宣国皇帝
That got us into this situation
才害得俺们落入这般境地
At this point, only this last plan remains
事到如今 只剩这最后一计
This plan, he taught it to me
此计 还是他教我的
Chu Meng
楚蒙
Do you know why I must go on the northern expedition?
你知道朕为什么一定要北伐吗
Your Majesty's achievements now surpass all past and present
陛下如今已经功盖古今
The northern expedition requires money
北伐要钱
Requires bloodshed
要流血
Requires the sacrifice of several generations to complete
要用几代人的牺牲才能完成
But I still must fight
但朕还是要打
Because this cannot be measured by profit
因为此事不能以利益计较
Because Xuan Kingdom's people
因为宣国的子民
They want to go home
他们想回家
They only recognize Xuan Kingdom as home
他们只认宣国这个家
Look, look outside
你看 看外边
Great victory, great victory
大捷 大捷
The royal army returns victorious
王师凯旋
Long live the Emperor
皇上万岁
In your lifetime
你这一生
You achieved great merits
立过大功
And committed great mistakes
也铸过大错
Some call you a ruthless tyrant
有人骂你是不择手段的暴君
But recovering the divine land
但克复神州
Is also an unparalleled achievement you created
亦是你造就的不世功业
Standing on this mountaintop
站在这山巅之上
You bear tens of thousands of people on your shoulders
你肩挑万万子民
Subject to the judgment of later generations, history's pen is iron
任凭后世评判 史笔如铁
Along the way
一路行来
Love, hate, success, failure
爱 恨 成 败
All rest on your single thought
皆在你一念之间
The consequences of every choice
每一个抉择的后果
You can only bear alone
你都只能自己消磨
Some heroes are made by history
有的英雄是历史造就的
While some heroes
而有的英雄
Make history
造就历史
The ambition to look north at the realm
江山北望之志
Will forever exist because of you
因你而永存